<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief history of the succession collected out of the records, and the most authentick historians, written for the satisfaction of the Earl of H.</title>
            <author>Somers, John Somers, Baron, 1651-1716.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60879</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4638</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11938</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11910698</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11910698</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50820</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60879)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50820)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 514:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief history of the succession collected out of the records, and the most authentick historians, written for the satisfaction of the Earl of H.</title>
                  <author>Somers, John Somers, Baron, 1651-1716.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Somers. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Kings and rulers --  Succession.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulers.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50820:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Brief HISTORY OF THE SUCCESSION, Collected out of the RECORDS, and the moſt Authentick HISTORIANS.</head>
            <head type="sub">Written for the Satisfaction of the EARL of <hi>H.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MEn generally, at preſent, buſy themſelves in diſcourſing about the Succeſſion, and therefore cannot but be pleaſed to have a ſhort Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of it ſet before them: For by ſeeing how the Crown has deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and in what manner,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Caeſ.</hi> de Bell. Gall. lib. 5. <hi>Tacitus</hi> in vitae <hi>Jul.</hi> Agricolae <hi>Strab.</hi> lib. 4.</note> and upon what grounds the natural Courſe of the Deſcent hath been changed, they will be enabled to judge what has been the Opinion of all Ages, in this ſo controverted a Point, and thereby may ſafely direct their Own.</p>
            <p>Nothing certain has come dow to us of the Nature of the Government of this Iſland before the <hi>Romans</hi> came hither; only this we learn from <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and <hi>Strabo,</hi> and <hi>Tacitus,</hi> That the <hi>Britans</hi> were ſubject to many Princes and States, not confederate, nor conſulting in common, but always ſuſpecting, and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently warring with one another.</p>
            <p>During the <hi>Heptarchy,</hi> whilſt every Kingdom was govern'd by different Laws, we cannot think they agreed in one Rule of Succeſſion: But, if that does not, I am ſure, the reading the many Changes and Confuſions of thoſe Times muſt convince any man, that their Rule was uncertain, or elſe that they had no Rule at all.</p>
            <p>Thoſe ſeven Kingdoms were at laſt united under <hi>Egbert:</hi> But yet our Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians who lived neareſt thoſe Times, expreſt themſelves ſo odly in this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and do ſo conſtantly mention the Election of almoſt every King before they tell us of his Coronation, that ſome learned men have doubted, whether be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Conqueſt the Government of this Iſland was ever grown up into a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled Hereditary Monarchy. Surely if it were ſo, yet all muſt agree, that<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pol. <hi>Virg.</hi> Hiſt. Angl. l. 4. in fine. <hi>Will. Malmeſ.</hi> l. 1. c. 2. fol. 16. l. 2. c. 1. fol. 36.</note> then the Succeſſion was not guided by the ſame Rules, as ſome men believe or pretend it ought now to be. <hi>Egbert</hi> himſelf, the firſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> Monarch, came to the Crown, not by Succeſſion but Election, being no way related to <hi>Briſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu,</hi> the laſt of the <hi>Weſt-Saxon</hi> Kings; and when he died, he gave the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons of <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Eſſex</hi> to his ſecond Son.<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hen. Hunt.</hi> l. 5 fol. 348. <hi>Will. Malmeſ.</hi> lib. 2. c. 3. f. 41.</note> 
               <hi>Ethelwolf</hi> divided the whole Iſland between his two Sons <hi>Ethelbald</hi> and <hi>Ethelbert.</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Will. Malmeſ.</hi> l. 2. c. 6. f. 48.</note> 
               <hi>Athelſtan</hi> (though a Baſtard) ſucceeded his Father, and was preferred to his ligitimate Brothers.<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Will. Malmeſ.</hi> l. 2. c. 6. f. 55. <hi>Rog. Hoved.</hi> par. 1. f. 423. <hi>Hen. Hunt.</hi> l. 5. f. 355.</note> 
               <hi>Edred,</hi> the younger Brother of King <hi>Edmond,</hi> was advanced to the Throne, though the deceaſed Prince had two Sons, <hi>Edwin</hi> and <hi>Edgar,</hi> who did both of them reign afterward ſucceſſively. <hi>Edgar</hi> left a Son at his Death; but yet there hapned a mighty Conteſt about his Succeſſor,<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>De Rege Eligendo mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na inter Regni Primores obor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta eſt diſſentio</hi> Simeon Dunelm. <hi>an. 975. f. 160 Edwardum</hi> Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerunt Electum conſecraverunt, &amp; lin Rogem unxerunt <hi>Sim.</hi> Dunelm ubi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra.</note> ſome of the great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> contending for the Election of <hi>Egelred</hi> his Brother. But at laſt the Intereſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50820:2"/>of <hi>Edward</hi> the Son prevail'd, and he was in a full Aſſembly elected, conſecrated, and anointed King. That which <hi>Ailredus,</hi> Abbot of <hi>Rievallis,</hi> in his Life of <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor, gives an account of, ſeems very remarkable to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. King <hi>Ethelred</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Glorioſus Rex <hi>Ethelridus Ailred</hi> Rievalis fo. <hi>372.</hi>
               </note> (who was no tame and eaſie Prince) deſirous to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh his Succeſſor in his Life-time,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Fit magnus coram Rege E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcoporum Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventus <hi>Reival.</hi> ubi ſupra.</note> ſummon'd a great Council expreſly for that purpoſe, and propoſes the thing to them. The Council were divided, ſome of them appearing for <hi>Edmond</hi> his eldeſt Son, and ſome for <hi>Alfred</hi> his ſecond Son by Queen <hi>Emma.</hi> But at laſt, upon ſome ſuperſtitious Fancy, they agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to paſs by both of them, and elected the Infant that was in the Queens Womb. To which Election the King gave his<note n="(h)" place="margin">Praebet Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctioni Rex con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſum <hi>Ailr.</hi> Ab. <hi>Reival.</hi> ubi ſupra.</note> Royal Aſſent, and the whole Aſſembly ſwore Fealty to the Child whilſt yet unborn. Undoubtedly this Story makes it plain, that it was not enough at that time to entitle one to the Crown, that he was the Kings Eldeſt Son, for the <hi>Ethelred</hi> would never have ſuffer'd a Debate about the Election of a Succeſſor, nor ſummon'd a Parliament expreſly for that purpoſe, which you ſee he though neceſſary to be done. And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all his care it ſeems upon the Death of <hi>Ethelred, Canutus</hi> had ſo great an Intereſt, that by an unanimous conſent in a full<note n="(a)" place="margin">Epiſcopi Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates Duces Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que nobiliores <hi>Angliae</hi> in unum congregati pari conſenſu Canu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum in Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um &amp; Regem Eligere omnem progeniem Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis <hi>Ethelredi</hi> repudiantes <hi>Sim. Dunelm</hi> an. <hi>1016.</hi> f. <hi>173. Brompt f. 903. Rog. Hovedon 1 par. f. 434.</hi>
               </note> Counſel he was elected King, and all the Iſſue of the laſt Prince rejected. 'Tis true, the <hi>Londo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> ſtood firm to <hi>Edmond</hi> Ironſide, (the approbation of that renowned City had then no little Influence on the Succeſſion) and there were divers Battels fought between them; but at laſt they came to an Agreement, and <hi>Edmond</hi> dying, the <hi>Dane</hi> ruled the whole Iſland peaceably whilſt he lived.</p>
            <p>Immediately upon the Death of <hi>Canutus,</hi> there was aſſembled at <hi>Oxford</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Placitum magnum de Regni Succeſſione apud <hi>Oxonium</hi> factum eſt <hi>Brompt. 932.</hi> Canuto mortuo facta est apud <hi>Oxonium</hi> mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na alteratio de Regni Succeſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne <hi>Hen. Knyht.</hi> de event <hi>Angl. Hen. Hunt l. 6. f. 364.</hi>
               </note> a great Council to determine who ought to ſucceed; where notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all the Intereſt which <hi>Godwin</hi> Earl of <hi>Kent,</hi> and the <hi>Weſt Saxon</hi> great men, could make on the behalf of <hi>Hardiknute,</hi> the legitimate Son of the dead King, they were over-voted, and <hi>Harald Harefoot</hi> (his Baſtard, begotten on <hi>Ailena</hi> or <hi>Elgiva</hi>) was elected. <hi>Harald</hi> dy'd in the 5th. year of his Reign, and<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Poſt mortem</hi> Heraldi Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deknute <hi>Electus Rex,</hi> Hen. Hunt l. 6. f. 365.</note> then the People were content to accept of <hi>Hardiknute</hi> for their King, and to that end ſent for him out of <hi>Flanders;</hi> but he dying Iſſueleſs, it was ordained in a<note n="(d)" place="margin">Omnes <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorum</hi> magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ad invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem tractantes de communi Concilio &amp; Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramento ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erunt, quod nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam tempori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus futuris ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis Dacus ſuper cos in Angliâ regnaret. <hi>Brompt. 934.</hi>
               </note> General Council, that never any <hi>Dane</hi> ſhould for the future be admitted to Reign in <hi>England.</hi> After which they proceeded to elect <hi>Alfred,</hi> the Son of <hi>Ethelred,</hi> and he being murder'd by the Treachery of Earl <hi>Godwin,</hi> they choſe his Brother <hi>Edward,</hi> commonly called <hi>Edward the Confeſſor.</hi> Nor were theſe Elections of theirs made with any reſpect to nearneſs of Bloud, more than thoſe whereof we have heard before; for <hi>Edmond Ironſide,</hi> their Elder Brother, had a Son then alive,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Brompt. 945.</note> whoſe Name was <hi>Edward,</hi> and who was Father to <hi>Edgar Atheling,</hi> living alſo at the ſame time. And though this <hi>Edward</hi> had an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Title to the Crown, if proximity of Blood could have given it, yet the <hi>Confeſſor</hi> was ſo far from ſuſpecting any danger from ſuch a Title, as that he invited his Nephew into <hi>England,</hi> and welcom'd him when he came with the greateſt expreſſions of Joy, and entertain'd him with the greateſt Confidence. Nor had the People any regard to this Royal Bloud upon the Death of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor,</hi> but elected <hi>Harald,</hi> the Son of Earl <hi>Godwin,</hi> who had no pretence of Kindred to the <hi>Saxon</hi> Line.</p>
            <p>Theſe few, among many other Inſtances which may be given, will ſhew plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enough, how men entituled themſelves to the Crown in thoſe days, and that then it was no ſtrange thing to hear of a Parliaments medling with the Succeſſon. Therefore I ſuppoſe the men who ſeem aſtoniſhed at the boldneſs of a Parliament, in preſuming to ſpeak of it at this time, will ſay, that they ought not to be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with Preſidents before the <hi>Norman</hi> Conqueſt; and that though the <hi>Saxons</hi> might be guilty of preferring a brave and deſerving <hi>Bastard,</hi> before a <hi>cruel</hi> or a <hi>ſilly legitimate</hi> Prince, and of many other Irregularities, yet no ſuch things are to be found in our Hiſtories ſince the time of <hi>William</hi> the firſt, whoſe Reign is the great <hi>Epoche,</hi> from whence we do compute our Kings. Let us therefore go on more particularly to obſerve what has been done ſince that time, and we hall ſee whether they who wonder ſo much, have any reaſon to do ſo.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:50820:2"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conquerour</hi> was himſelf illegitimate, and yet ſucceeded his Father in the Dutchy of <hi>Normandy,</hi> and therefore had no reaſon to ſet any great value upon that fort of Title, which is derived from a Right of Bloud. And it ſeems he did not much regard it; for paſſing by <hi>Robert</hi> his eldell, he gave the Crown<note n="(a)" place="margin">A patre ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tima valetudine decumbente in Succeſſorem adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatus. Guil. Malmab. <hi>lib. 4. fol. 120.</hi> Sim. Dunel. <hi>anno 1087. fol. 213.</hi> Brompt. <hi>f. 980.</hi>
               </note> by his laſt Will, to <hi>William Rufus</hi> his younger Son, diſpoſing only with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to his own Inclinations, the Crown which himſelf had gain'd.</p>
            <p>But his Son was too wiſe to rely upon this Diſpoſition as a ſufficient Title, and therefore had recourſe to a more ſute one:<note n="(b)" place="margin">Convocatis terrae magnatibus. <hi>Brompt. 983.</hi> Optimates fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Weſtmonaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium</hi> in Concili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um convenere, ubi loci post lorgam Conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinnem <hi>Guili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elinum Rufum</hi> Regem fecere. <hi>Mat. Paris,</hi> Flores hiſt. fol. <hi>231.</hi> Volentibus omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Provincianum animis in Regem acceptus. <hi>Mat. Paris</hi> in vit <hi>Gull 2.</hi> fol. <hi>14.</hi> anno <hi>1088.</hi>
               </note> For calling together the Nobles and wiſe Men of the Kingdom, he acquainted them in a full Council, with his Fathers Will, and deſired their Conſent to it; who after a long Conſultation, did at laſt unanimouſly agree to make him their King, and thereupon he was Crown'd by <hi>Langfranck,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> I cannot but obſerve one thing farther, that though ſome men make uſe of the abſolute Victory which the <hi>Conquerour</hi> had made, and affirm, that thereby the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were wholly bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and all the old Laws and Cuſtoms of the Realm were deſtroy'd, yet it is plain that at this time the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt was ſo great, that it kept the Crown upon <hi>William Rufus</hi>'s Head, in ſpight of all that the <hi>Normans</hi> could do in behalf of <hi>Robert,</hi> though they univerſally joyn'd with him.<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Rex fecit convocare Anglos. <hi>Sim. Dunelm</hi> an. <hi>1088.</hi> fol. <hi>214.</hi>
               </note> For the King calling together the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and opening to them the Treaſon of the <hi>Normans,</hi> and<note n="(d)" place="bottom">Angli cum fideliter juvabant, <hi>&amp;c. Sim. Dun.</hi> ubi ſupra.</note> promiſing them a compleat Reſticution of their ancient Laws, they ſtood firm to him, and ſoon put an end to all the Attempts of his Brother, and his <hi>Norman</hi> Accomplices.</p>
            <p>Upon the Death of <hi>William Rufus, Robert</hi> had a fair pretence to renew his Claim to the Crown,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Hic <hi>Rober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> ſemper con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traraus &amp; adeo innaturalis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titerat Baroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Regni An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae, quod ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nario conſerſie &amp; conſilio toti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Communita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Regn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ipſum refutaverunt &amp; pro Rege omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no reouſaverunt, &amp; <hi>Henricum</hi> fratrem in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem erexerunt, <hi>H. de Knyght. c. 8. 2374.</hi> Poſt mortem <hi>Willielmi Rufi</hi> electus eſt <hi>Henricus</hi> frater ejus <hi>M. Paris 55.</hi> in vita <hi>H. 1.</hi> an. <hi>1100.</hi> &amp; <hi>62.</hi> anno <hi>1105, Mat. Weſt, 235.</hi> Apud <hi>Winton.</hi> in Regem electus eſt. <hi>Brempt. 997.</hi>
               </note> but that Prince had diſcover'd too much of the <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty of his Dispoſition, of his averſion to the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Nation, and of his proneneſs to Revenge;</hi> ſo that by the full Conſent and Counſel of the whole Body of the Realm, aſſembled at <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> he was finally rejected, and they did concur to elect the <hi>Conqueror</hi>'s third Son <hi>Henry</hi> for their King, (as <hi>Mar. Weſtminſter</hi> expreſſes it) Nor did they do this but upon Terms; for both the Clergy and Laity ſaid, that if he would reſtore them their ancient Liberties, and confirm them by his Charter, and abrogate ſome ſevere Laws which his Father had made, <hi>they would conſent to make him King.</hi> And this prudent and learned King was not aſhamed or unwilling to own this Title; for he does at large recite it in his Charter whereby he confirms their Liberties,<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Rich. Hagulſtad <hi>310.</hi> Brompt. <hi>10.21.</hi> Mat. Paris <hi>240.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sciatis me miſericordia Dei, &amp; communi conſilio Baronum Regni Angliae, ejuſdem Regni Regem Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natum eſſe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt you ſee had reaſon to believe and own the Power of the Kingdom, in ſetting the Crown upon what head they pleaſed, and therefore he deſired to ſecure it that way to his Poſterity. To that end, in the <hi>13th.</hi> year of his Reign,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Coacio Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio fecit omnes Principes &amp; Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes Anglicani Regni adjurare terram &amp; Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num <hi>Willielmo</hi> filio ſuo, <hi>&amp;c. Gervas Cron. 1138.</hi>
               </note> he ſummon'd a Council, and procured all the great and powerful men of the Kingdom to ſwear that his Son <hi>William</hi> ſhould ſucceed him: But afterwards this Son of his was unfortunately drown'd, and the King dy'd, leaving no other Iſſue but <hi>Maud</hi> his Daughter, who had been mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to the Emperor, and afterward to <hi>Geoffery Plantaginet,</hi> Earl of <hi>Anjou.</hi> No diſpute can be made, but that ſhe had all the Right which proximity of Bloud could give; yet <hi>Stephen,</hi> Earl of <hi>Boloign,</hi> who was the Son of <hi>Adela,</hi> one of the <hi>Conquerors</hi> Daughters, and whoſe elder Brother <hi>Theobald,</hi> Earl of <hi>Blois,</hi> was then living, ſtept in before her, and by repreſenting to them the Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience of a Feminine Government, and promiſing them to conſent to ſuch good
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50820:3"/>and gentle Laws as they ſhould deviſe, prevail'd<note n="(d)" place="margin">A primori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Regni cum fuvere Cleri &amp; populi Electus eſt à <hi>Wil. Cant.</hi> Archiepiſcopo in Regem Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>R. Hagul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtad, an. 1156. f. 312.</hi> Conſentientibus in ejus promotionem <hi>Willielmo Cantuarienſis</hi> Archiepiſcopo &amp; Clericorum &amp; Laicorum univerſitate apud <hi>London, Jo. Hagulſtad 250.</hi> Predictus <hi>Stephanus</hi> à cunctis in Regem Electus, <hi>Gervas Chron. f. 340.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregatis <hi>Londiniis</hi> terrae magnatibus, <hi>Mat. Paris 74.</hi>
               </note> with the Eſtates of the Realm to elect him King. And in this Charter, which he made ſoon after, he owns this Title, beginning it thus, <hi>Ego</hi> Stephanus <hi>Dei gratia, aſſenſu Cleri &amp; Populi in Regem Angliae electus,</hi> &amp;c. And the <hi>Pope,</hi> in his Charter of Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, ſent to him in the firſt year of his Reign, tells him, That he was <hi>Communi voto &amp; unanimi aſſenſu tam Procerum quam etiam Populi in Regem electus.</hi> And then he adds, That ſince ſo univerſal an Aſſent could not be directed but by the Divine Grace, he therefore allows his Title, and confirms him in the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>'Tis true that afterwards <hi>Mawd</hi> the Empreſs, together with her Son <hi>Henry,</hi> having, after ſome years, gained many to their ſide, gave him great diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance; till at laſt <hi>Stephen</hi> having loſt his Eldeſt Son <hi>Euſtace</hi> (in whom he pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced his hopes<note n="(e)" place="margin">Hen. Hunt. l. 8. f. 395. R. Hag. de geſtii. Steph. 314.</note> and uſed all means, whilſt he liv'd, to have got him declared his Succeſſor, but without Succeſs) came to an Agreement with the Empreſs and her Son, and<note n="(a)" place="margin">Facto <hi>Wintoniae</hi> conventu publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, Rex <hi>Stepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> ipſum Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem cunctis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentibus adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tavit in Filium, utque, interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſito omnium Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramento, conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit &amp; confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ei totius <hi>Angliae</hi> principatum, Dux autem ſuſcepit eum in loeum genitoris, contendens ei omnibus diebus vitae fuae nomen &amp; rem Regij culminis obtinere, <hi>Gervaſ. f. 1375.</hi> In conventu Epiſcoporum &amp; aliorum de Regno optum <hi>Mat. Weſtm. f. 246.</hi> an. <hi>1153.</hi> &amp; <hi>282.</hi> an. <hi>1154.</hi> Conſenſerunt in hoc omnes principes Regni <hi>Jo. Hagulſtad f. 282. Mat. pacis 86. Hen. Hunt. l. 8. f. 398. Jo. Hagalſtad 282. an. 1154.</hi>
               </note> the Parliament, (who alone could give a Sanction to ſuch Agreement,) was aſſembled at <hi>Wincheſter</hi> to confirm it; and then <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> publickly Adopts <hi>Henry</hi> for his Son, and with their full conſent declares him his Heir; and with the ſame conſent <hi>Henry</hi> gives <hi>Stephen</hi> the name of Father, and agrees that he ſhould continue to be King, during his Life, and they all Swore, That if <hi>Henry</hi> ſurviv'd, he ſhould without oppoſition obtain the Crown, and <hi>Stephen</hi> by his Charter, which is ſet down at large in <hi>Brompton</hi> publiſhes this Agreement, <hi>Brompt.</hi> 1037.</p>
            <p>In all this Tranſaction certainly there was no conſideration had of any other Right, but that which univerſal conſent conferred; For if <hi>Stephen</hi>'s <hi>Heir</hi> had any pretence, he had a Son then living, whoſe Name was <hi>William,</hi> and who by the ſame Agreement was to have all the Poſſeſſions which his Father enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before he was made King. If the <hi>Heir</hi> of <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt had any Title, that was veſted in <hi>Mawd</hi> the Empreſs, who was then alſo living; ſo that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the parties had any other colour of Right to the Crown, than what the conſent of the People gave them.</p>
            <p>According to this Parliamentary Agreement and Limitation, <hi>Stephen</hi> enjoy'd the Crown peaceably during his Life, and after his Death <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Second</hi> came to it as peaceably; but he remembred by what Title, and therefore was deſirous to ſecure it to his Son in the ſame manner, that he took a very dangerous and unuſual way to do it.<note n="(b)" place="margin">Convene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt interim die statuto ex mandato Regis <hi>Londoniam</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius <hi>Angliae</hi> Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopi Abbates Comites Barones vicecomites pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſiti Aldermanit cum ſidejuſſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, <hi>Gervas H 2. f 1412.</hi>
               </note> For Summoning a Parliament to meet at <hi>London,</hi> he procures his Son <hi>Henry</hi> to be declared King together with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, by their conſent, and thereupon he was Crowned by the Archbiſhop of <hi>York,</hi> and Fealty Sworn to him by all. This was the occaſion of Civil Wars between them, for the Father meant hereby only to have ſecured the Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to him, and the Son was impatient of having only the bare Title of a King, all along pretending to an Equal Authority, as doth ſufficiently appear by what he writes to the Prior and Convent of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> where he takes notice, That his Father did attempt ſome Invaſions upon them, which he ought not to have done without his aſſent.<note n="(c)" place="margin">Gervas H. 2. f 1425.</note> 
               <hi>Qui, ratione Regiae unctionis, Regnum, &amp; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Regni curam ſuſcepiemus,</hi> and therefore he appeal'd to the Pope in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half. Nay, the Father himſelf paid that Reſpect to his Sons Dignity, That when he at laſt ſubdued him and his Rebellious Brothers,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Brompt. f. 1100.</note> he would not ſuffer him to do him Hommage with his other Sons, (though he offered it.) But <hi>Henry</hi> the Son dying in the Life of his Father, <hi>Richard</hi> was then his Eldeſt Son ſurviving, and conſequently had all the Right which a next Heir could claim.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50820:3"/>But the wiſe and wary King had not confidence enough to rely upon this (now ſo much talk'd of) ſacred Right; but though he had already ſuffered ſo much from diſobedient Sons, was glad to get the Succeſſion confirmed to him in his Life-time. And, the Truth is, there was reaſon enough that he ſhould do ſo; for he had all his Children by <hi>Eleanor</hi> the Daughter of <hi>William</hi> Duke of <hi>Guyen,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">M. Paris 84</note> who was before the Wife of <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>7th</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> who was ſtill living, and ſhe onely Divorced <hi>cauſa Adulterii,</hi> which being not a Divorce <hi>à vinculo Matrimonii,</hi> ſhe could not, either by the Canon-Law uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally received, or the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> lawfully Marry with any other Husband.</p>
            <p>After his Father's Death, <hi>Richard</hi> came to <hi>London,</hi> to which place all the Clergy and Laity were ſummoned; and<note n="(b)" place="margin">Poſt tamcle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri quam populi ſolennem &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitam Electio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem <hi>R. de daeto f 647. R. H. par. 2. f. 6. 56.</hi>
               </note> after he had been ſolemnly and duely Elected by the whole Clergy and Laity, (they are the very words of the Hiſtorian) and taken the uſual Oaths, he was Crowned. And when he undertook the holy War, he<note n="(c)" place="margin">Flo. Hiſt. An. 1190.</note> declared <hi>Arthur</hi> Son of his next Brother <hi>Geof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fery</hi> the Duke of <hi>Britain,</hi> the next Heir to the Crown.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard</hi> dying without Iſſue, this <hi>Arthur</hi> ought to have ſucceeded, and his Siſter <hi>Elianor</hi> alſo had a Title before her Uncle: But <hi>John</hi> the younger Brother, without regarding this divine Right of his Nephew, applies himſelf to the People for a more ſure, though but a humane Title,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Praelatorum Comitum &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liorum Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um multitudo inſinita, <hi>Brompt. 1281.</hi>
               </note> who being ſummon'd together, elected him King. And<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat. Paris, 197. An. 1199.</hi> Si aliquis ex ſtirpe Regis Defuncti aliis praepolliret pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius &amp; prom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptius in electio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ejus eſſe conſentiendum.</note> 
               <hi>Hubert</hi> the then Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> did at his Coronation, preach a Doctrine, which would have ſounded very ſtrangely to the Convocation in 1640. <hi>(viz.)</hi> No one could make any title to the Crown, <hi>niſi ab univerſitate Regni unanimiter Electus.</hi> And that he who was moſt worthy ought to be preferred. But (as he goes on) if any one of the Race of the deceaſed King, was more deſerving than others, as <hi>John</hi> the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the deceaſed King was, the People ought more readily to elect him, than a Stranger to the Royal Bloud. This was all the Title King <hi>John</hi> preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and this was then ſufficient to put by his Nephew. And in his<note n="(f)" place="margin">Charta Moderationis feodi Magni fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilli, <hi>an. 1 Jo.</hi> ex vet. Reg. in Archivis Arch. <hi>Cant. he ſays he came to the Crown,</hi> Jure Hereditarin &amp; mediante tam Cleri quam Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli unanimi Conſenſu &amp; Favore.</note> Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, he does more than once own, that he owed his Crown to the election and favour of his Subjects.</p>
            <p>But when King <hi>John</hi> gave over to diſſemble his Nature, and went about to change his Religion<note n="(g)" place="margin">N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enon &amp; Legem Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum, Quam, vanam cerſuit retinquens, Legi <hi>Mahometis</hi> fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deliter adhaere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, <hi>Mat. Par. 243.</hi>
               </note> (for he made offers of that ſort to the King of <hi>Moroc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co</hi>) when he diſcovered himſelf not to be that worthy man which the People ſuppoſed him to have been; they remembred whence he derived his Title, and proceeded, upon the ſame reaſon that they had choſen him, to make a new Election,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Mat. Par. 279. Flo. Hiſt. an. 1216.</note> chuſing <hi>Lewis</hi> Son of <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> who was next Heir to the Crown in the right of <hi>Blanch</hi> his Wife, Neece to King <hi>John,</hi> and Daughter to his Siſter <hi>Elianor,</hi> both the Children of <hi>Geoffery</hi> Duke of <hi>Britain,</hi> being dead before that time.</p>
            <p>When King <hi>Philip</hi> heard of their choice, he conſented to ſend his Son, being the rather induced thereto by this reaſon,<note n="(i)" place="margin">Velens fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem ſuum Regem <hi>Ricardum</hi> à Regno <hi>Angliae</hi> injuſte privare &amp; inde de proditiane accuſatus &amp; coram eo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victus, Damnatus fuit per judicium in Curia ipſius Regis, <hi>Mat. Weſtm. 275. Mat. Par. 281.</hi>
               </note> That <hi>John</hi>'s Bloud being cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by an Attainder of Treaſon in the Life-time of his Brother <hi>Richard,</hi> he was uncapable of taking the Crown by Deſcent, and unworthy to take it any other way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lewis</hi> coming to <hi>London,</hi> was there Elected and Conſtituted King, ſwearing to preſerve the Peoples Laws, and they ſwearing Allgiance to him: But he ſoon forgot his Coronation-Oath, and attempted ſeveral ways to introduce an Arbitrary Government, before he was well Eſtabliſhed in his Throne, which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> aſſoon reſented: And King <hi>John</hi> happening to die very opportune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50820:4"/>The <hi>Earl-Marſhal,</hi> calling together the Great men of the Kingdom, and placing <hi>Henry</hi> the third, then an Infant, in the midſt of them, perſwaded them to make him King, who was altogether innocent of his Fathers faults:<note n="(k)" place="margin">Mat. Weſt. 275. Hen. de Knyght f. 2426 <hi>c.</hi> 15. <hi>l.</hi> 2.</note> The Earl of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> ſaid this was contrary to their Oath to <hi>Lewis:</hi> To which the Marſhal replied, that <hi>Lewis</hi> by breaking his Oath had abſolved them from theirs; and that he deſpiſed the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to ſet up the <hi>French;</hi> and that he would be the deſtruction of the Realm. With whoſe Reaſons the whole Aſſembly being convinced, cried out unanimouſly, <hi>Fiat Rex;</hi> and accordingly they Crown'd King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and ſoon after compelled <hi>Lewis</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renounce all pretences to the Crown.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> the Third dying,<note place="margin">Hen. de Knight <hi>f.</hi> 2472. <hi>c.</hi> 16. <hi>l.</hi> 2.</note> after a long and troubleſome Reign, his Son <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt, a Prince of great hopes, and whoſe Life anſwered the higheſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations, ſucceeded; but whether he was the eldeſt Son of his Father, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains a doubt in Hiſtory. The Houſe of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> who derived themſelves from his Brother <hi>Edmond,</hi> pretending always that <hi>Edmond</hi> was the Elder, and <hi>Edward</hi> the Younger Brother, and that <hi>Edmond</hi> was put by the Crown, by <hi>common Conſent,</hi> for his Deformity.</p>
            <p>After the Death of <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt,<note place="margin">Tho. Walſingh. in Vit. Ed. 2. f. 126.</note> his Son <hi>Edward</hi> the Second ſucceeded, but he degenerating from ſo great a Father, the People grew weary of his Irregular and Arbitrary Government. And a Parliament being by him ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pol. Virg. l. 18. f. 352.</note> as all our Writers ſay, or as <hi>Polydor Virgil</hi> words it, <hi>Principes Convocato Concilio pervenerunt</hi> Londini (which I obſerve, only that we may know what <hi>Polydor</hi> means, when he makes uſe of the expreſſion of <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes in Concilio Congregati;</hi>) They preſently entred into a conſideration of the miſerable ſtate of the Nation;<note place="margin">Froiſſart 1. vol c. 14. Fructus Temporum. Part 7. f. 107. Hen. de Knight l. 3. c. 15. f. 2549.</note> and a Paper being publickly read, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining many Inſtances of the King's Miſgovernment, all which he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, they concluded he was unworthy to Reign any longer, and that he ought to be depoſed; and ſent to him to let him know their Reſolution, and to require him to renounce his Crown and Royal Dignity, otherwiſe they would proceed as they thought good. And they appointed Commiſſioners to go to him in their Names: The <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Ely</hi> for the <hi>Biſhops;</hi> The <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Warren</hi> for the <hi>Earls;</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Piercy</hi> for the <hi>Barons;</hi> and Sir <hi>William Fruſſel</hi> for the <hi>Commons,</hi> to reſign their Homage up to him: which <hi>Fruſſel</hi> pronounced in all their Names, and formally deprived him of all Royal Power; the form of which is particularly ſet down by <hi>Knighton.</hi> The King read this ſad Sentence with extraordinary grief, and many complaints of thoſe evil Counſellors who had ſeduced him; but in the midſt of his Sorrow<note n="(a)" place="margin">Quod Fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſuum <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardum</hi> poſt ſe Regnaturum Eligiſſemt, <hi>Knyght 2550.</hi>
               </note> he gave them thanks that they Elected his Son to reign after him. Thus was that glorious Prince <hi>Edward</hi> the Third elected King in his Fathers Life-time, <hi>Et huic Electioni univerſus populus conſenſit. Walter</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who preached the Coronation-Sermon, took this for his Text; <hi>Vox Populi vox Dei.</hi> By this we may ſee that all his Predeceſſors were not of Archbiſhop <hi>Lawd</hi>'s minde, but thought there was a Divine Right ſomewhere elſe than where he placed it. Upon the death of <hi>Edward the black Prince,</hi> there was ſome Diſpute whether <hi>John of Gaunt,</hi> the eldeſt ſurviving Son of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, ſhould Succeed <hi>Jure propinquitatis,</hi> or <hi>Richard</hi> the Son of the <hi>Black Prince;</hi> whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Edward</hi> the Third procured the Parliament to confirm the Succeſſion to <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> the <hi>Second.</hi> And afterwards, when <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Third</hi> dyed,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pol. Virg. 20. f. 295.</note> 
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Juri Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditario ac eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am voto com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muni ſingulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, <hi>H. Knyght l. 5. f. 2630.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Polido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus Virgil</hi> ſays,<note place="margin">Rot. Parl. 1 <hi>H.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>Principes Regni habito Concilio apud</hi> Weſtm. (you know what <hi>Polidor</hi> means by <hi>principes</hi>) <hi>Richardum, Edwardi principis Filium, Regem di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt, by their</hi> common Suffrages.<note place="margin">Pol. Virg. l. 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In the 21 year of <hi>Richard</hi>'s Reign, a Parliament being aſſembled at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> they drew up, by their common Conſent, a Form whereby he did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50820:4"/>the Crown, and the name and power of King, diſcharging all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from all Oaths which they had taken of Allegiance to him, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing himſelf thereby inſufficient for the Government; and ſwearing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to make any pretences to the ſame for the future. All which he Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced and Subſcribed, wiſhing, (if it were in his power,) to have <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> for his Succeſſour; but ſince it was not, he deſired the Commiſſioners to ſignifie his Deſires to the States of the Realm. The next day all the States of the Realm accepted his Reſignation, and when that was done, they proceeded to read publickly his Coronation-Oath, and all the Breaches of it, that ſo it might appear how juſtly he had deſerved to be depoſed. All which are contained in Thirty three Articles, entred at large in the Rolls of Parliament, (and well deſerve to be read) whereupon the States adjudged that he ſhall be Depos'd, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point Commiſſioners <hi>ad Deponendum eundem</hi> Richardum <hi>Regem ab omne Dignitate, Majeſtate &amp; honore Regiis, vice nomine &amp; authoritate omnium ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum praedictorum, prout in Conſimilibus caſibus de antiqua conſuetudine dicti Regni fuit obſervatum:</hi> which the Biſhop of St. <hi>Aſaph</hi> did, in full Parliament, in their names, and by their directions. The ſame Commiſſioners were alſo to reſign up to him their Homage and Fealty, and intimate the Sentence of Depoſition; which they did accordingly, by the Mouth of Sir <hi>William Thirning,</hi> whoſe words are at large entred upon Record. Then did the Parliament proceed to chooſe <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth King; And upon this Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle onely did he rely, though he mentioned ſome other trifling ones, as that he challenged it, being then void, by Force, as Deſcended to him from King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third.</p>
            <p>But this could give him no Title, for 'tis plain that whilſt any of the Iſſue of <hi>Lionel</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> the Third Son of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, were in being, no right of Blood could Deſcend to him, who derived his Pedigree onely from <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> who was but his Fourth Son. And he plainly ſhewed what a good Opinion he had of a Parliamentary Title to the Crown, when in the <hi>7th</hi> year of his Reign,<note place="margin">7 H. 4. cap. 2.</note> he procured an Act of Parliament to paſs, whereby the Inheritance of the Crown and Realms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France</hi> were ſetled upon himſelf for Life, and the Remainder entail'd upon his four Sons by name, and the Iſſue of their Bodies begotten. He was contented that it ſhould be limited no farther, but that after failure of his own Iſſue, it ſhould go according to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral direction of the Law. And he made a Charter ſoon after, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he ſetled the Crown purſuant to this Act of Parliament:<note place="margin">Bucks Hiſt. R. 3. l. 2. f. 50.</note> 
               <hi>Poſt ipſum ſucceſſive haeredibus ſuis de ipſius Corpore legitime procreandis;</hi> which Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was again confirm'd in Parliament, the 22 <hi>December,</hi> 8 <hi>H.</hi> 4. and the Original Charter is ſtill to be ſeen in the <hi>Cotton</hi> Library.</p>
            <p>Immediately upon the Death of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, a Parliament met at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and there, according to the cuſtom of the Realm, it was debated who ſhould be King: But all Men had entertained ſo good thoughts of Prince <hi>Henry,</hi> that without ſtaying till the whole Aſſembly had declared him King, divers of them began to ſwear Allegiance to him. A thing ſtrange, and without Preſident, as only occaſioned by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Opinion which was generally conceived of him before.</p>
            <p>And the certain Title veſted in him by an Act of Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Princeps</hi> Henricus, <hi>facto Patris ſui funere, Concilium Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum apud</hi> Weſtmonaſterium <hi>Convocandum Curat, in quo de
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50820:5"/>Rege Creando, more Majorum, agitabatur. Continuò aliquot Principe ultro in ejus Verba jurare coeperunt, quod Benevolentiae Officium Nulli, priuſquam Rex renunciatus eſſet, praeſtitum conſtat. Adeo</hi> Henricus <hi>ab ineunto aetate ſpem omnibus optimae Indolis fecit,</hi> Pol. Virg. l. 22. Hiſt. Angl. in Vit. H. 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> the Fifth dying, and leaving but one Son, who was an Infant of Eight Months old, <hi>Titus Livius</hi> ſays there was ſome doubt whether he ſhould be accepted as King;<note place="margin">Titus Liv. Mſ. in Bibl. Bod. Cott. Record. f. 666.</note> but as ſoon as his Fathers Funerals were So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnized, the Eſtates of the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> Aſſembling and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting together, they declared <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth to be their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign.</p>
            <p>In the Thirty fifth year of <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth, a new Limitation of the Crown was made by Parliament, for though the King had a Son then living, yet it was Enacted,<note place="margin">Hubington's Hiſt. E. 4. f. 10.</note> That during his own Life onely, <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth ſhould hold and enjoy the Crown, and that during his Life, <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>York</hi> ſhould be reputed and ſtil'd Heir Apparent to the Crown, and that it ſhould be Treaſon to compaſs his Death;<note place="margin">Cott. Rec. 670. Fructus Temp. part 7. f. 162.</note> and after the Death, Reſignation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of <hi>Henry,</hi> the Crown was limited in Remainder to <hi>Richard</hi> and his Heirs, with a Proviſo, that if <hi>Henry,</hi> or any in his behalf, ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to diſanul or fruſtrate this Act, that then <hi>Richard</hi> ſhould have the preſent poſſeſſion of the Crown. And by force of this Act of Parliament, the ſame Duke of <hi>York,</hi> taking advantage of <hi>Henry</hi>'s Violation of it, did lay claim to,<note place="margin">Hubingt. <hi>E.</hi> 4. f. 73.</note> and attempt the recovery of the Kingdom, as alſo did his Son <hi>Edward</hi> after him with better ſucceſs; and <hi>Edward</hi> did openly inſiſt upon this Title in the Speech which he made at his Coronation.</p>
            <p>It was alſo Declared by <hi>Edward</hi>'s firſt Parliament, in the firſt year of his Reign, that <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth having broken the aforeſaid Concord in many particulars, the Crown was duely devolved to <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth by vertue thereof.</p>
            <p>Afterwards <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth being driven out of the Kingdom, in the Tenth year of his Reign, the Parliament did again entail the Crown on <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth, and the Heirs Male of his Body, with the Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> Brother to <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth, who was thereby alſo declared Heir to <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>York.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis worthy obſervation, that both the Families of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter</hi> clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a Title by Act of Parliament; and as long as that Title continued, the Iſſue of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth had never any Diſturbance from the Pretences of the Houſe of <hi>York,</hi> who had undoubtedly the Right of Blood on their ſide:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Buck</hi>'s Hiſt. <hi>Rich.</hi> 3. lib. 1. fol. 20.</note> But as ſoon as <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>York</hi> had a Title veſted in him, by the Statute made in the Thirty ninth year of <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth, then he thought it was worth contending for; nor did he and his Son deſiſt till they had dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven out <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth did recover the Kingdom again as ſuddenly as he loſt it, and prevail'd with his Parliament to repeal that Law which was made during his Expulſion, and ſo left the Crown to that young unfortunate Prince <hi>Edward</hi> the Fifth, who held it not long enough to have it put on him with the uſual Solemnity; for though he was Proclaimed, he was never Crowned King: For his Uncle <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> having ſecured him and his Brother in the <hi>Tower,</hi> did cunningly inſinuate the Baſtardy of his Nephew, and that <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth had another Wife living at the time of his Marriage to their Mother, and alſo at the time of their Birth.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:50820:5"/>
            <p> The Report found Credit univerſally, in ſo much that the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> coming to him at <hi>Baynards</hi>-Caſtle, with moſt of the great Lords and wiſe men of the Kingdom, and the Mayor and Aldermen of <hi>London,</hi> the Duke did in their Names acquaint him, that they had unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly thought fit to elect him King, as being Heir to the Royal Blood of <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>York,</hi> upon whom the Crown was entail'd by the High Authority of Parliament.</p>
            <p>'Tis very remarkable, that in the midſt of their higheſt Flatteries and Courtſhip to him, they tell him only of this great and ſure Title by Act of Parliament; although if he had been indeed (what was pretended) the Heir of the Houſe of <hi>York,</hi> his Right by Deſcent from <hi>Edward</hi> the Third was unqueſtionable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard</hi> (after ſome feigned Excuſes) did at laſt accept of their Offer and Election; and the Parliament being ſoon after Aſſembled,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cott.</hi> Rec. fol. 709.</note> they preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Bill to this effect: <hi>Pleaſe it your Grace to underſtand the Conſideration, Election and Petition under-written, of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and of the Commons,</hi> &amp;c. And thereby they Declare the Children of <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth illegitimate,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bucks Rich.</hi> 3. lib. 1. fol. 22.</note> and that his Brother <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence</hi> was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted of High-Treaſon by Parliament, in the 17th year of <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth's Reign, <hi>by reaſon whereof all the Iſſue of the ſaid</hi> George <hi>were and are diſabled and barr'd of all Right and Claim, that in any caſe they might have or challenge by Inheritance to the Crown and Dignity Royal of this Realm, by the ancient Laws and Cuſtoms of the ſame.</hi> After which, conſidering that none of the uncorrupted lineal Blood of <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>York</hi> could be found but in his Perſon, (ſay they) We have choſen and do chooſe you our King and Sovereign Lord. Then the Bill proceeds, in reciting that all the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Laws do approve his Title, and declaring him King as well by Right of Conſanguinity and Inheritance, as by lawful Election, and entails the Crown on him and the Heirs of his Body, and declares his Son Heir Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent. To which the King gave his Royal Aſſent in theſe words: <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> idem Dominus Rex, de Aſſenſu dictorum trium Statuum Regni, &amp; Authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te praedicta, omnia &amp; ſingula praemiſſa, in Billa praedicta contenta concedit, &amp; ea pro vero &amp; indubio pronunciat, decernit, &amp; declarat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the barbarous Murder of his Nephews did ſoon beget ſuch an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Deteſtation of <hi>Richard</hi> in the minds of the People, that they reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved he ſhould no longer Reign over them; and ſo, taking hold of a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence which <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Richmond</hi> ſet up, they joyn'd with him againſt <hi>Richard.</hi> Though <hi>Henry</hi>'s Title was indeed no more than a meer Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; for not only the Right of the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>York,</hi> (as far as Blood could give Right) was before that of the Houſe of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo he had no manner of Intereſt in that Title which the <hi>Lancaſtrian Line</hi> had, ſince his Claim was under a Baſtard, begotten in Adultery; and beſides, his Mother, <hi>Margaret</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Richmond,</hi> as Heir to whom he pretended he claim'd, was then living. Therefore <hi>Comines,</hi> the moſt judicious Writer of that Age, and who knew well what was the ſence of <hi>Europe</hi> concerning his Title, ſays plainly, (though he wrote in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh) <hi>Qu'il <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Croix, ne Pile, ne nul Droit, (comme Jeo Croy) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:50820:6"/>
            <p> Nevertheleſs, <hi>Henry</hi> having ſlain <hi>Richard</hi> in <hi>Boſworth</hi>-field, the Crown was there put on his Head by the Lord <hi>Stanley,</hi> with the general Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the People. But he was wiſe enough to think his Title to it was not very good, till it was made ſo by an Act of Parliament, and therefore in the firſt year of his Reign he procured one to paſs in theſe words:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the Wealth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bucks Rich.</hi> 3. lib. 5. fol. 145.</note> 
               <hi>Proſperity, and Surety of this Realm of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>and for avoiding of all Ambiguities and Queſtions,</hi> (The wiſeſt of our Princes you ſee had no little Opinion of the Authority of a Parliament in this point,) <hi>Be it Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That the Inheritance of the Crown of the Realms of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> France, <hi>with all the Preheminences and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnities Royal to the ſame appertaining, and the Ligeances to the King belonging, beyond the Seas,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall be, reſt, remain and abide in the moſt Royal Perſon of our Sovereign Lord</hi> Henry <hi>the Seventh, and in the Heirs of his Body lawfully coming perpetually, with the Grace of God, and ſo to endure, and no other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus did the wiſeſt of our Kings eſtabliſh himſelf,<note place="margin">Lord <hi>Bacon H.</hi> 7. f. 11, 12.</note> and the beſt of our Hiſtorians mentions it as one of the greateſt Inſtances of his Wiſdom, That he did not preſs to have this as a Declaration or Recognition of Ancient Right, but onely as an Eſtabliſhment of the poſſeſſion which he then had; nor to have the Remainder limited to any perſon after the determination of his Eſtate, but was content with the Settlement upon himſelf, and the Iſſue of his own Body, leaving it to the Law, to decide what was to follow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the failure of ſuch Heirs.</p>
            <p>Nor can any thing be more clear, than that <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Seventh</hi> depended entirely on this Parliamentary Title, without extending any pretences of his, or his Wives, (who was Heir of the Houſe of <hi>York,</hi>) beyond this Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment, in as much as the Oaths of Allegiance and other publick Teſts and Securities, which were required at that time of the Subjects, were not in general Terms, to the King, his Heirs, and Succeſſors, but only to the King,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Burnet</hi>'s. Hiſt. of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. ad lib. 2. fol. 3, 4.</note> and the Heirs Male of his Body lawfully begotten. An Inſtance of this, (without going any further) may be ſeen amongſt the Records Printed at the end of the late Hiſtory of the Reformation, where Cardinal <hi>Adrian,</hi> when he was promoted by <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh to the Biſhoprick of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells,</hi> renounces all Clauſes in the Popes Bulls, which may be prejudicial <hi>Domini meo ſupremo, &amp; Haeredibus ſuis corpore ſuo legitime procre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atis,</hi> Angliae <hi>Regibus;</hi> and he does afterwards ſwear Allegiance to him in the very ſame Words, without taking any notice of Remoter Heirs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eighth,</hi> the Heir to this Entail, Succeeded his Father; and though he attempted as much for Arbitrary Power, and uſed Parliaments with as little reſpect as any of his Predeceſſors; Yet even he never
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50820:6"/>doubted of their Power in ſettling the Succeſſion, but valued it much, and reſorted to it frequently.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>25th</hi> year of his Reign an Act paſſed,<note place="margin">St. 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. cap. 22.</note> wherein the Parliament ſay, they were <hi>bounden to provide for the perfect ſurety of the Succeſſion;</hi> (they did not certainly reckon themſelves bound to do a thing that was not in their Power.) And then they take notice of the great Miſchiefs and Effuſions of Bloud which had happened by reaſon of the doubtfulneſs of the true Title; and <hi>for the avoiding of all future Queſtions,</hi> do Enact, <hi>That the Imperial Crown of this Realm ſhall be to King</hi> Henry <hi>8th, and the Heirs of his Body Lawfully begotten on Queen</hi> Anne, <hi>and the Heirs of the Bodies of ſuch ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Sons reſpectively, according to the courſe of Inheritance; and for default of ſuch Iſſue, then to the Sons of his Body in like manner; and upon failure of ſuch Iſſue then to the Lady</hi> Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth, <hi>and after her to any other Iſſue, in Tail, and then the Remainder is limited to the right Heirs of</hi> Henry the <hi>8th.</hi> By the ſame Statute every Subject at his full Age is oblig'd to take an Oath to defend the Contents of it, and the refuſal is made Miſpriſion of Treaſon. And the next <hi>Parliament,</hi>
               <note place="margin">26 <hi>H.</hi> 8. c. 2.</note> which was held in the year following, does particularly Enact an Oath for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Some few years after theſe Acts were Repealed,<note place="margin">28 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Raſt.</hi> Crown 4.</note> and the <hi>Parliament Entailed</hi> the <hi>Crown</hi> upon the King, and the Heirs of his Body by <hi>Queen Jane;</hi> And Power is given the King for want of Iſſue of his Body to diſpoſe of the Succeſſion by his Letters Patents, or his laſt Will.</p>
            <p>It is alſo made Treaſon, if any Uſurp upon thoſe to whom it is ſo appointed. Here the <hi>Parliament</hi> do not only uſe their power of changing the Succeſſion, but they <hi>Delegate it to another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the <hi>thirty fifth</hi> Year of this King's Reign,<note place="margin">35 <hi>H.</hi> 3. cap. 1.</note> the <hi>Parliament</hi> by another Act take notice of the great and high Truſt which the Subjects had in him, in putting into his hands wholly the Order and Declaration of the Succeſſion; Yet the King being then ready to go into <hi>France,</hi> they do Enact, that after his Death, and the Death of <hi>Prince Edward,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Iſſue, the Crown ſhould be to the <hi>Lady Mary,</hi> and the <hi>Heirs</hi> of her Body; but both ſubject to ſuch Conditions as the King ſhould limit by his Letters Patents, or by his laſt Will, ſign'd with his Hand: And if the <hi>Lady Mary</hi> performed not thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50820:7"/>that then the Crown ſhould go to the <hi>Lady</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>as if the Lady</hi> Mary <hi>had been dead without Iſſue;</hi> and if the Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> neglected to perform ſuch Conditions, then it ſhould go to ſuch other Perſon as the King ſhould appoint, in the ſame manner as before, as if the Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> had <hi>been dead without Iſſue.</hi> And Authority is given to him, by his Letters Patents, or his laſt Will, ſigned with his own Hand, to appoint the Crown to remain to ſuch Perſon or Perſons, and for ſuch Eſtate, and under ſuch Conditions as he ſhould pleaſe.</p>
            <p>An Oath alſo for obſerving this Statute is appointed, and it is made <hi>Treaſon</hi> to refuſe it, or to diſturb or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt any Perſon to whom it is limited by this Act, or ſhould be by the King, purſuant to the Power given him thereby.</p>
            <p>This is abundantly ſufficient to prove, That it was <hi>the univerſal Opinion of that Age, That the Succeſſion was wholly under the Controul of Parliament,</hi> who not only limited it as they pleaſed themſelves, but <hi>ſubjected it to Conditions,</hi> and <hi>to the Appointments of others.</hi> But the thing was in its own Nature ſo evident, that they who had the greateſt Reaſon, and were moſt concern'd to do it, did never preſume to queſtion the Power of a Parliament in this Point.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lethington,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Burn.</hi> Hiſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form. Collect. 268.</note> 
               <hi>Secretary</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in a Letter of his, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to Sir <hi>William Cecill,</hi> then <hi>Secretary</hi> of State here, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he argues in behalf of the Title of his <hi>Miſtriſs,</hi> Mary <hi>Queen of</hi> Scots, to ſucceed Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> againſt a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Diſpoſition made by the laſt Will of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, to his <hi>Neece,</hi> the Lady <hi>Frances,</hi> Daughter to the <hi>French Queen,</hi> if his own Iſſue fail'd, ſays of theſe Statutes that gave the King Power to diſpoſe of the Crown, That they were againſt Equity to diſinherit a Race of Forreign Princes, and that they were made in an abrupt Time, (as he terms it;) but yet he confeſſes, that ſince the thing was done, it was now valid and unavoidable, unleſs ſome Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances did annihilate the Limitation and Diſpoſition made by King <hi>Henry</hi>'s Will.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:50820:7"/>
            <p> And ſo he proceeds to prove that the power which was given to the King by theſe Statutes, was not purſued, (which it ought to have been moſt ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and in a preciſe Form,) for that the King never ſigned the Will, but that his name, ſet to it, was forged: Nay, I will venture to ſay that in all the Books which were written to ſupport the Claim of the <hi>Scottiſh Queen</hi> againſt <hi>King Henries</hi> Will, (though the whole power and wealth of the <hi>Guiſes</hi> were employed to ſet every wit at work on that Deſign) there was never any ſtreſs laid upon it,<note place="margin">Treatiſe of the Title of Queen <hi>Mary</hi> to the Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>pag.</hi> 38, 39. <hi>&amp;c. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Dodd.</hi> Engl. Lawyer. <hi>pag.</hi> 8.</note> or ſo much as a pretence that theſe Acts of Parliament were void or ineffectual in themſelves. In that Diſcourſe which was publiſhed by <hi>Philips,</hi> and compoſed by Sir <hi>Anthony Brown</hi> one of the Juſtices of the Common Pleas, who was (in judge <hi>Dodderidges</hi> opinion) a perſon of an incomparable ſharpneſs of Wit, There was all the help that learning either in Divinity, Civil or Common Laws could give; yet there the Authority of the Parliament in the caſe, and the validity of theſe Statutes is all along admitted. Indeed they endeavour to put ſome other conſtruction upon the Statutes, but their great Argument is, That King <hi>Henry,</hi> as King, had no power to diſpoſe of the Crown, and therefore theſe Laws only gave him an Authority, and made him only as it were a Commiſſioner, and therefore, as all other Authorities, (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially being in Derogation of the courſe of the Common Line,) was to be ſtrictly followed. They allow that he had ſufficient power to Deviſe, and that he might Honourably have uſed that Power; but that he ever did exerciſe that Authority, is the thing denyed. But it is time for us to go on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth ſucceeded his Father, and took upon him a power, which ſurely no King ever had, to diſpoſe of his Crown by the Will. But that diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition ſerving to no other purpoſe but to the Ruine of the <hi>Lady Jane Gray,</hi> His <hi>Siſter Queen Mary</hi> firſt, and after <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi> enjoy'd the Crown according to the Limitation of the Statute 35 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 1. and that one of them had no other Title, muſt be agreed by all: For Queen <hi>Catherine</hi> was alive at the time when <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was born: ſo that if the firſt Marriage was unlawful, Queen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and if the ſecond was unlawful, Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> muſt neceſſarily have been Illegitimate.</p>
            <p>I cannot but obſerve one paſſage to our preſent purpoſe, which I meet with in the time of Queen <hi>Mary.</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Montague</hi> firſt Lord Chief Juſtice of the Common Pleas,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mores</hi> Reports 827. <hi>&amp;</hi> 828.</note> and afterwards of the Kings Bench (one who had the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of the ableſt and wiſeſt Lawyer of his Age,) being accuſed to have drawn the Will of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, whereby that Queen was to have been diſinherited, and being in great danger upon that account; drew up a State of his own caſe, and therein ſets forth that the great reaſon which prevailed with him to obey the King in that particular, and upon which he did ſtill rely for his indemnity, was, that if Queen <hi>Mary</hi> came to the Crown,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eullers</hi> Church-Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory <hi>lib.</hi> 8. <hi>fol.</hi> 5.</note> ſhe took it by force of the Act of Parliament which did limit it to her in Remainder, ſo that ſhe came in as a purchaſer and not in privity of eſtate to her Brother, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently could not puniſh Treaſons or offences committed in his time.</p>
            <p>I muſt needs alſo obſerve, that in the Articles made upon the Marriage of Q. <hi>Mary</hi> with <hi>Ph.</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> which were confirmed by Act of Parliament,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Mar. Parl. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Crowns and Territories of <hi>Philip</hi> are diſtributed part to <hi>Charles</hi> the Infant of <hi>Spain,</hi> part to the <hi>Iſſue</hi> of the intended Marriage. Whereby it does appear not only what opinion all <hi>Europe</hi> had of the power of an Engliſh Parliament, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that by the conſent of the Eſtates of other Realms, Crowns might be limited and diſpoſed out of the ordinary courſe of Deſcent.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>firſt</hi> year of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> The Parliament recognize her Title to the Crown,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 3.</note> with expreſs Relation to the <hi>Statute</hi> 35 <hi>H.</hi> 8. which inveſts it in her and the heirs of her Body, and do enact that the Limitation made by that Statute ſhall ſtand and remain as Law for ever, and all Sentences,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 5.</note> Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Decrees to the contrary are declared to be void, and appointed to be cancell'd. And the ſeveral offences which are made Treaſon by another Statute in the ſame year, are all reſtrain'd to the Queen and the Heirs of her Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy only. The Parliament intending to extend that new ſecurity no further
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50820:8"/>than her Eſtate in the Crown (which ſhe took by that Parliamentary limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) did extend.</p>
            <p>In her <hi>Thirteenth</hi> year it was Enacted,<note place="margin">13 <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 1. <hi>Raſt.</hi> Treaſon. 27.</note> That if any perſon claim Title to the Crown for himſelf or any other, during her Life, or ſhall not upon Demand acknowledge her Right, <hi>He ſhall be diſabled during his Life to have the Crown in Succeſſion, as if he were naturally Dead.</hi> And to affirm Right of Succeſſion in ſuch claimer or uſurper, (after Proclamation made of ſuch claim or uſurpation,) is made Treaſon. Nor does the Statute ſtop there, but makes it Treaſon, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the life of the Queen, and forfeiture of all Goods and Chattels after her deceaſe, to affirm that the Queen, with and by the Authority of Parliament, is not able to make Laws and Statutes of ſufficient force and validity to limit and bind the Crown of this Realm, and the Deſcent, Limitation, Inheritance and Government thereof, or that this or any other Statute made by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with the Queens aſſent, is not or ought not to be for ever of ſufficient force to bind and Govern all perſons, their Rights and Titles that may claim any <hi>Intereſt</hi> or <hi>Poſſibility</hi> in <hi>or to the Crown in Poſſeſſion, Remainder, Inheritance, Succeſſion or otherwiſe.</hi> It were well if ſome raſh men, who preſume in their diſcourſes to reſtrain the power of the Parliament, (that is, the King, Lords and Commons,) in the great buſineſs of the Succeſſion, would be ſo wiſe as to remember this Act, (which is ſtill in force) and the penalty to which they ſubject themſelves by ſuch ſawey Talk. That incomparable States-man the Lord <hi>Burleigh</hi> had another kind of opinion of the Security which an Act of Parliament could give his Royal Miſtreſs,<note place="margin">Compleat Ambaſſad. <hi>fol.</hi> 219.</note> by making the Scottiſh Queen <hi>(the Popiſh Succeſſor of that time)</hi> unable and unworthy of the Succeſſion; as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in a Letter which he wrote about this time to Sir <hi>Francis Walſingham,</hi> then Ambaſſadour in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Twenty Seventh</hi> year of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">27 <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1.</note> it was enacted that if any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion was made, or Rebellion or other thing tending to the hurt of Her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon by or for, or with the privity of any one who ſhould or might pretend Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to the Crown, and the ſame ſhould be adjudged in ſuch manner as that Law appoints, then every perſon againſt whom ſuch Judgment ſhould be given, ſhould be <hi>excluded and diſabled for ever to have or claim the Crown;</hi> And that the Subjects of this Realm lawfully might by all forcible and poſſible means, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue all ſuch offenders: And their Iſſues aſſenting or privy thereto, are in like manner diſabled and to be purſued. And this Act was made in purſuance of an Aſſociation enter'd into by the People in the vacancy of Parliament out of their great zeal for the preſervation of the life of that excellent Princeſs.</p>
            <p>By vertue of his Statute <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scotland</hi> was afterwards executed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Strangways</hi> Hiſt. of <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scotland, fol.</hi> 179.</note> as appears by the Commiſſion for her Tryal.</p>
            <p>King <hi>James</hi> her Son who was a wiſer Prince, and not wholly <hi>govern'd by Prieſts as his Mother was,</hi> though he had the ſame pretences that ſhe had, yet never diſputed his Right, or ſet on foot any Title during the life of the ever Renowned Queen; <hi>though ſhe would never ſuffer him to be declared her ſucceſſor.</hi> He was too wiſe to incur the like diſability as his Mother had done, and <hi>to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt a Title Eſtabliſht by Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Death, The Act of Recognition made upon King <hi>James</hi> his coming to the Crown, doth particularly inſiſt upon that Title, which was raiſed by Act of Parliament to <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Seventh,</hi> and the Heirs of his body, and that immediately upon the <hi>Queens</hi> deceaſe the Crown deſcended and came to King <hi>James;</hi> ſo that you ſee the Title of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> is again ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by Parliament; And the entail made by the Statute of 35 <hi>H.</hi> 8. being ſpent upon her death without Iſſue, King <hi>James</hi> comes in as next Heir to the old entail made the <hi>firſt</hi> year of <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh.</p>
            <p>Thus have I ſet down before you the whole courſe of the Engliſh Succeſſion as plainly, as truly, and as briefly as is poſſible. I ſhall leave every man to make his own obſervations on this Hiſtorical Deduction: But this one obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation I believe all men muſt make from it, That it hath been the conſtant opinion of all ages that the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> had an unqueſtionable
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50820:8"/>power to Limit, Reſtrain and Qualify the Succeſſion as they pleaſed, and that in all Ages they have put their power in practice; and that the Hiſtorian had reaſon for ſaying that ſeldom or never the third Heir in a right Deſcent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd the Crown of <hi>England.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Daniel, fol. <hi>5.</hi> in vita H. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>It were as eaſie to ſhew that in all other Kingdoms the next of Blood hath been frequently excluded from the Succeſſion, but the Hiſtory of our own Countrey is our buſineſs; yet I cannot forbear reciting the <hi>Speech</hi> which <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors</hi> ſent from the States of <hi>France,</hi> made to <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> when they had ſolemnly rejected him (though he was Brother to <hi>Louys d' Outremes</hi> and next Heir to the Crown) and had elected <hi>Hugh Capet</hi> for their King. They told him that every one knew that the Succeſſion of the Crown of <hi>France</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to him, and not <hi>Hugh Capet.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gerr. du Hail. lib. <hi>6.</hi> an. <hi>988.</hi>
               </note> But yet (ſay they) the very ſame Laws which give you this Right of Succeſſion, do judge you alſo unworthy of the ſame; for that you have not hitherto endeavoured to frame your manners ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Preſcript of thoſe Laws, nor according to the uſages and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms of your Countrey, but rather have ally'd your ſelf with the <hi>German</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion our old Enemies, and have loved their vile and baſe manners. Wherefore ſeeing you have forſaken the ancient virtue and ſweetneſs of your Countrey, we have alſo forſaken and abandon'd <hi>you;</hi> and have choſen <hi>Hugh Capet</hi> for our King, and put you back, and this without any ſcruple of Conſcience at all, eſteeming it better and more juſt to live under him, enjoying our Ancient Laws, Cuſtoms, Priviledges and Liberties, than under you the Heir by Blood in oppreſſion, ſtrange Cuſtoms and Cruelty. For as thoſe who are to make a Voyage at Sea do not much conſider whether the Pilot be owner of the Ship, but whether he be skilful and wary; ſo our care is to have a Prince to Govern us gently and happily, (which is the end for which Princes were appointed) and for theſe ends we judge this man fitter to be our King.</p>
            <p>Certainly it were a moſt dangerous thing to have an opinion prevail, that the King in concurrence with his Parliament ſhould not have power to change the direct order of Succeſſion, though the preſervation both of him and his people did depend upon it. For it does directly tend to Anarchy, and makes the Government to want power to defend it ſelf, by making ſuch Alterations as the variety of Accidents in ſeveral ages may make abſolutely neceſſary. There muſt be a ſupreme uncontroulable power lodged ſomewhere. And the men who talk at this rate, can hardly find where it is lodged in <hi>England,</hi> if not in the King, Lords and Commons in Parliament.</p>
            <p>But when a man begins to ask a Reaſon of this Doctrine of theirs, that proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of Blood does give a Title unchangeable by any Humane Laws; The tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of it differ exceedingly; ſome of them tell us of a Divine Patriarchal Right, which Kings as Natural Fathers of their People have derived down to them from <hi>Adam.</hi> And this Notion though it be no older than the preſent Age, has been very frequent in mens Mouths and Books, and has much pleaſed of late (as new things uſe to do). But they conſider not that if this be true, there never can be but one Rightful Monarch in the Univerſe, That is He only who is the direct and Lineal Heir of <hi>Adam</hi> then living. And thus theſe great Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons of Abſolute Power, inſtead of ſupporting, do ſhake the Thrones of all the Princes in the world, ſince none of them at this day can make out any ſuch Title.</p>
            <p>There are others who being deſirous to beſtow upon the Crown a Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the like nature, which they were at the ſame time obtaining from it, have declared in general, That Monarchy is of Divine Right, That Princes ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed by the Laws of God, That their Title is not ſubject to any earthly cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance, nor owing to any conſent of the People. But the conſequences of this opinion are not once conſider'd by theſe men, that thereby the property of all Subjects, and the Laws of all Countreys, are deſtroy'd together. For no Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Laws or Contracts can bind or reſtrain a Power divinely Inſtituted.<note place="margin">Card. Pullav. Hiſt. conc. Trid. l. <hi>18.</hi> cap. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> (Or if you like it better in the words of a great Cardinal) A Jurisdiction which is of Divine Right, is not alterable by the will or power of man.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:50820:9"/>
            <p> Beſides all communities which live under another Form of Government, muſt be guilty of violating this Divine Inſtitution. And perhaps there are few others beſides the Great <hi>Turks</hi> Dominions, which are govern'd as they ought to be.</p>
            <p>In what a damnable condition are the <hi>Venetians</hi> and the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> who admit no Monarch at all? <hi>Poland</hi> and the <hi>Empire,</hi> who Elect their Princes, and will not hear talk of this Divine Right of Succeſſion?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aragon,</hi> where they do not only elect their King, but tell him plainly at his Coronation, that they will Depoſe him if he obſerves not the conditions which they require from him, and have a ſetled Officer call'd <hi>El' Juſtitia</hi> for that purpoſe? Nay, even <hi>France</hi> it ſelf, which 'tis notoriouſly known, does exclude Women from this Divine Right?</p>
            <p>That Government is of Nature, and derived from God, is manifeſt. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more natural in Man than the Deſire of Society, and without Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Society would be intolerable. But can it be proved from hence that the Government cannot be moulded into ſeveral Forms agreeable to the Intereſt and Diſpoſitions of ſeveral Nations, and may not be varied from time to time as occaſion requires, by the mutual conſent of the Governours, and of thoſe who are Governed?</p>
            <p>And after all pretences of this kind, let any place of Scripture be produced wherein God obliges a people to this or that Form, till they have firſt obliged themſelves to it by ſome Act of their own?</p>
            <p>I do agree that if God by any extraordinary Revelation has ordain'd any ſort of Government, or by any immediate Denomination has conferr'd a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom on any Family, and has directed in what order the Crown ſhall diſcend, that all men are bound to ſubmit to it and acquieſce in the Divine Will, as ſoon as it is clearly and evidently made out to them, but they muſt not be angry if men expect ſuch an Evidence.</p>
            <p>There is a third ſort of men, who tell us this Realm being entirely ſubdued by the Conquerour, and by him left to deſcend to his Heirs, none of theſe Heirs who derive a Title under him, can deprive thoſe who are to ſucceed of any Right which they ought to have, but muſt leave the Crown as free to them as they themſelves received it from their Anceſtors.</p>
            <p>I will not here inſiſt upon the danger that any Prince runs into who founds his Title in force, becauſe it will be hard to prove that ſuch a one does not leave as good a Title open for every man who can make himſelf ſtrong enough. Nor need I trouble my ſelf to ſhew, that all Conqueſt does not put the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour into an Abſolute Right. Though it be moſt evident in the caſe of <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Firſt,</hi> who did by his Sword proſecute a claim of another nature, and meant only to acquire that Right, and after conqueſt reſted in it. He pretended to the Crown as the Gift of King <hi>Edward,</hi> and to vindicate that Title he enter'd with Arms. And though his Relation to the Crown was more remote than that of <hi>Edgar Atheling,</hi> (then a child) yet his Title was better than <hi>Harolds</hi> the preſent Uſurper, who could pretend no kindred at all, and who had himſelf Sworn to ſupport the Grant to <hi>William.</hi> Nor did he claim a Power by conqueſt, (though the name of Conquerour was given him by after times, ſays <hi>Daniel</hi>) but ſubmitted to the orders of the Kingdom, deſirous rather to have his Teſtamentary Title, than his Sword to make good his ſucceſſion. But I will admit that he made an abſolute conqueſt, and then theſe men will grant that he might himſelf diſpoſe of this conquer'd Kingdom. Therefore if he did not leave it to deſcend in ſuch a manner as they would have it go, nor did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute any ſuch ſort of Succeſſion, ſurely this Argument of theirs will fall to the ground. Now 'tis plain that he never deſign'd that the Crown ſhould deſcend, but gave it to his ſecond Son, and thereby gave an early example <hi>of excluding and pretermitting the unworthy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, Others object that the Fundamental Laws of the Land againſt which no Act of Parliament can be of force, have ſo eſtabliſht the Succeſſion that the courſe of it cannot be alter'd. This is ſurely a new diſcovery unknown to our Fore-fathers, as the foregoing Hiſtory does abundantly prove. But let
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50820:9"/>theſe objectors be asked by what Authority theſe imaginary Laws were made? For if an Authority equal to that which made them be ſtill in being, That Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority may certainly repeal them when ever it pleaſes to exert it ſelf. If the King alone made them, no doubt but that he may change them too. If they will ſay they were made by the diffuſive body of the people, they run be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are aware into the guilt of worſhipping that Idol The Multitude, and make a great ſtep towards placing the foundation of the Government upon contract and conſent. But then let them produce thoſe Laws or ſome Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick memorial of them, before it be exacted from us to believe there were ever any ſuch.</p>
            <p>Yes, they will ſay, there is ſuch an ancient Law acknowledged by all the Judges, and known to every man, that the Deſcent of the Crown purges all Defects whatſoever. This Maxim as it is uſually repeated is in theſe words, and this might be admitted, and yet could not be pertinently apply'd to a caſe where the Deſcent it ſelf is prevented by a Law. But I will not take ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of their words, but will conſider the Objection, as it ſtands in that Book where the firſt mention of it was made,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> H. <hi>7.</hi> f. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> b. Que le Roy fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt perſon able &amp; diſcharge d'auſcun at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainder eo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto qu' il priſt ſur lui le Reign &amp; eſtre Roy.</note> and that is in the <hi>Year Book</hi> of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Seventh,</hi> it being ſaid there by the Judges, That the King was a perſon Able and Diſcharged of any Attainder <hi>eo facto,</hi> that he took upon him the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and to be King.</p>
            <p>Firſt, This was not only an extra-judical opinion, but was not pertinent to the Queſtion referr'd to their conſideration, Whether thoſe who were cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen into the Houſe of Commons, and were at that time attainted of Treaſon might ſit in Parliament, till their Attainders were Reverſed; and they all agree that their Attainders ſhould firſt be annulled. But then they proceed to ſay that there was no neceſſity that the Kings Attainder ſhould be Reverſed, for that he might enable himſelf, and needed not any Act of Reverſal. But ſurely they ſaid very wiſely in what they ſaid, for he who had won a Crown in the field, had gone a great way towards enabling himſelf to wear it. Moſt ſure it is that if an Act of Reverſal were neceſſary before he could ſit, that then it was impoſſible he ever ſhould ſit there, becauſe no ſuch Act could be made without the Royal Aſſent. <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Seventh</hi> was then King <hi>de facto,</hi> and in poſſeſſion of the Throne, and it was ſomewhat of the lateſt to conſider whether he was qualified or not. Certainly it had been ſtrange ſelf-denyal in the Judges, and a neglect of themſelves, (which is not uſual with them) to have alledged an Incurable Diſability in the King, from whom they had their Patents and Authority.</p>
            <p>In the next place let us conſider what precedent the Judges cite to juſtifie this opinion of theirs, and how appoſite it is. <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Sixth</hi> being driven out of the Kingdom by <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Fourth,</hi> The Conquerour call'd a Parliament, and got an Act to paſs, whereby <hi>Henry</hi> was diſabled to hold the Crown. About ten years after, <hi>Henry</hi> regains the Kingdom, and upon this re-acceſſion to the Crown (as 'tis uſually call'd) This Act is never repeal'd. But does not eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Child ſee the Reaſons of it? For if <hi>Henry</hi> was Lawful King, (and before he was not to doubt that) The Act it ſelf was void in as much as it wanted the Royal Aſſent. So that for him to have procured an Act of Repeal had been to affirm a Title to the Crown in <hi>Edward.</hi> But without doubt this opinion of the Judges as it is apply'd by the Objectors, was new and unheard of before. We ſee the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>France</hi> was otherwiſe informed by the learned men in the time of King <hi>John,</hi> for they thought his Blood corrupted,<note place="margin">Mat. Weſtni. <hi>275.</hi> v. ſupra.</note> and him uncapable of taking the Crown by Deſcent, becauſe he was Attainted of Treaſon, which prevailed with that King to ſend over his Son <hi>Lewis,</hi> to put in his claim in right of his wife, who was the next Heir. It alſo ought to be obſerved that the true Reaſon why the generality of the Nation did ſo long approve the Title of the Houſe of <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſter,</hi> was becauſe all the Princes of the Houſe of <hi>York</hi> were Attainted of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and their Blood corrupted. But as ſoon as ever this corruption was purged, and <hi>Richard Duke</hi> of <hi>York</hi> was declared Heir Apparent by Parliament, the people ſoon forſook the <hi>Lancaſtrians,</hi> and ſet the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>York</hi> in the Throne.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:50820:10"/>
            <p> Nay, the very learned men of the ſame Age with theſe Judges, though quite otherwiſe, as will appear beyond contradiction in this ſamous caſe which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows. <hi>Richard</hi> the <hi>Third</hi> had two Elder Brothers, <hi>Edward</hi> and <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence. Richard</hi> deſigning to ſecure the Crown to himſelf, had procured the Children of <hi>Edward</hi> to be declared Illegitimate, yet ſtill the Duke of <hi>Clarence</hi> had Iſſue living which might pretend. But obſerve what the Parliament ſay (as to this) in the firſt year of <hi>Richard</hi> the <hi>Third:</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. Sup. &amp; Cott. Rec. <hi>709.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>That in the ſeventeenth year of <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Fourth, George</hi> Duke of <hi>Clarence</hi> was Attainted of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, by reaſon whereof all the Iſſue of the ſaid <hi>George</hi> was, and is Diſabled and Barred of all Right and Claim, that in any caſe he or his Iſſue might have or challenge by Inheritance to the Crown and Dignity Royal of theſe Realms. After that we conſider that you be the undoubted Heir, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> And ſo they proceed affirming that all Learned men in the Laws do approve his Title. You ſee within leſs than three years before this opinion of the Judges, The whole Parliament do not only give their opinion, but aſſure you that all Learned men of that time held clearly that an Attainder did hinder the deſcent of the Crown, and incapacitate the perſon to take it. Nay, what goes yet further in this matter, <hi>Richard</hi> himſelf, though he was as jealous to ſecure his Title as ever Tyrant was, and had as good advice to diſcern the moſt diſtant danger: though he was always reſtleſs in endeavouring to get the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Richmond</hi> into his Hands, who was a very remote pretender, and only deſcended from a Baſtard of the Houſe of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> yet he fear'd nothing on this ſide. He knew how he had wrong'd the Children of his Brother <hi>Edward,</hi> and could not be at eaſe till he had ſent them out of the World, but he let the Children of his Brother <hi>Clarence</hi> live, without apprehending any danger from them becauſe their blood was corrupted, and all poſſibility of Deſcent taken from them by the Attainder of their Father. It was this only preſerved them alive, and not any remorſe of Conſcience or any niceneſs in ſending another Nephew out of the World after thoſe whom he had diſpatcht before. This notable caſe attended with theſe circumſtances, will convince every man either that the Judges intended no ſuch thing by their opinion as ſome men fancy, or elſe at leaſt that extra-judicial opinions were then as Apocryphal as they have been ſince.</p>
            <p>Conſider Laſtly, the unreaſonableneſs of this Doctrine which tends directly to ſubvert Government, and to put the life of the King Regnant into the hands of his Succeſſor. The next Heir may commit Rapes and Murders and Treaſons, Burn Cities or Betray Fleets, may conſpire againſt the life of his Prince, and yet after all, if by <hi>Flight</hi> or <hi>Force</hi> he can ſave himſelf, till ſome of his accomplices can get the King diſpatcht, in ſpight of all Laws and Juſtice he muſt come to the Crown, and be Innocent.</p>
            <p>But when I reflect what ſort of men I am arguing with, and how willingly they uſe to ſubmit to Authority, I think I ſhall convince them beſt by citing the opinions of two great men, the one a Cardinal, the other a Lord Chancellour, both of them Martyrs for the Papal Supremacy, I mean <hi>Fiſher</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Moor.</hi> And if their Judgments approve the power of Parliaments in the buſineſs of the Succeſſion, it cannot but weigh very much on ſuch occaſions as this. 'Tis well known how reſolution even to death they refuſed the Oath of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion which the Parliament had framed,<note place="margin">Burn. Hiſt. Ref. lib. <hi>2.</hi> fol. <hi>156.</hi>
               </note> becauſe therein the Kings Supremacy was avow'd, and therefore they cannot be ſuſpected to diſſemble, when at the very ſame time they declared, that if that of Supremacy was left out, they would willingly Swear an Oath to maintain the Succeſſion of the Crown to the Iſſue of the Kings preſent Marriage, as it was then eſtabliſht by Parliament, and gave this reaſon for it, that this was in the power of a Parliament to determine; but not who was ſupreme head of the Church. Sir <hi>Thomas Moor</hi> went further, and own'd a very ſtrange opinion of their power in this point. But he ſays expreſly at the ſame time, that the Parliament had unqueſtionable Authority in the ordering of the Succeſſion, and that the people were bound to obey them therein.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:50820:10"/>
            <p> After the Teſtimonies of theſe two great Papiſts, it will be little to add the Teſtimony of a Proteſtant. But yet I will mention what Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi> (who was no inconſiderable man, though a Proteſtant) ſays in his Incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Preface to the Hiſtory of the World: Without doubt (ſays he) Humane Reaſon would have judged no otherwiſe but that <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Fourth</hi> had rendred the Succeſſion as unqueſtionable by the Act of Parliament which he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured to entail it on his Iſſues, as by his own Act he had left his enemies pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erleſs.</p>
            <p>But ſinking men catch hold of every thing, and when they cannot object to the validity, they will tell us, That ſuch an Act of Parliament to diſinherit the next Heir is unjuſt and without a ſufficient ground.</p>
            <p>I will not at preſent enter into the diſpute how far the difference of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which will alſo neceſſarily draw on a change in the Government, does juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie men in ſeeking to preſent the two deareſt things on earth in an orderly and lawful way. I will not (though I ſafely might) challenge theſe men to tell me, where ever any ſettled Nation which had Laws of their own, and were not under the immediate force of Conquerour, did ever admit of a King of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Religion than their own. I will not inſiſt on it that the Crown is not a Bare Inheritance, but an Inheritance accompanying an Office of Truſt, and that if a mans defects render him uncapable of the Truſt, he has alſo forfeited the Inheritance. I need not ſay how far a Nation is to be excuſed for executing Juſtice ſummarily, and without the tedious formalities of Law, when the neceſſity of things requires haſte, and the party flies from Juſtice, and his confederates are numerous and daring, and the Princes life in danger.</p>
            <p>But this I will ſay, that if the Parliament have power in this thing, which I need not prove, by ſhewing that the ordinary courſe of Law allows Heirs to be diſinherited of Fines and Recoveries, and that the Parliament in all ages has frequently done it by making Acts to alter the ſtrongeſt Settlements, where Equity has Dictated it, though the Heirs were never in any wiſe criminal. There according to Sir <hi>Thomas Moors</hi> opinion the people are bound in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to obey their Laws, and muſt not pretend to enquire whether they were made upon juſt grounds. For by the ſome Rerſon they may pretend that all other Laws were made without juſt cauſe, and refuſe obedience to any of them. And ſurely thoſe that ſhould do ſo, would be an Excellent <hi>Loyal Party.</hi> God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend this Nation from ſuch Loyalty, as oppoſes it ſelf to the King and the Laws, and God defend the King from the pretended Duty and Submiſſion of thoſe men, who whilſt they talk of his power ſo much Renounce it openly, and oppoſe what would be the greateſt ſecurity of his perſon, and in effect ſet up his Succeſſor above him, even in his life time.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
